This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SE-Radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
[music]
Hi, this is Priyanka Raghavan for
Software Engineering Radio. And my guest
today is Dwayne McDaniel, a developer
advocate, hands-on practitioner, and
also host of the Security Repo podcast.
We're here to talk about the engineering
challenges of secrets management. Dwayne
regularly presents on secrets sprawl and
secure engineering at events like RSA,
BSides, OWASP, KubeCon, etc. So, welcome
to the show, Dwayne.
Thank you very much. I'm glad to be here
today.
At SE Radio, we have done episode 578 on
secrets management with distributed
cryptography. We did an episode 311 on
secrets management. And recently, we did
an episode 680 on security and privacy
of AI coding assistants. However, it's
2026 and we've already had two big
supply chain attacks, one with the PyPI
ecosystem last week, and then recently,
was just yesterday that we saw the Cloud
Code getting leaked, the repo. And it
appears that both of these were because
of secrets leakages, and therefore, this
show is well-timed.
Yes, there's been many, many things
going on. I'd even hesitate to say as
few as two. It's ongoing campaigns.
There was a time when you could refer to
a specific product like SolarWinds,
because that's what it affected,
Codecov. Yes, there was one thing, but
now we're seeing the proliferation
through the ecosystem at a rate that
calling it the trivia attack or the Aqua
attack or the Light LLM attack or the
Axios attack is underselling what's
going on here. It's a massive campaign
that literally breakneck speeds. I have
never seen anything propagate this fast
through the ecosystem. So, it feels all
very interconnected. Cisco, that was
news yesterday as well as as time of
recording this, and that all feels very
very interconnected. The idea of that's
steal credentials from people who have
the keys to, well, all of the
infrastructure that makes the internet,
that makes all of these ecosystems.
Therefore, we can propagate at our
leisure. There's been a massive increase
in the number of crypto mining schemes
directly related to this. It's just
we're watching
machine speed attacks using
old-fashioned API keys that never
expire.
Wow. So, I think we then have to
probably spend some time on some of
these case studies, which we'll do later
on in the show. But, I actually wanted
to ask you a couple of definitions for
all our first-time listeners who are not
aware of secrets management. So, the
first thing I wanted to ask you is, what
do you mean by secrets and secret
sprawl?
When I say secrets, we're talking about
the large bucket of credentials, access
mechanisms. There's a really good
definition I like from Ev, the CEO of
company called Teleport. He says, it's
any piece of data that by itself can be
used to gain access or to grant access.
That's a very succinct definition. So,
anything that you can put into plain
text that someone else could simply pick
up and use immediately. My favorite
example of this is uh Postgres database
connection URL because those tend to
bake in the credentials right there in
the URL. Same thing with GitLab links if
you do it wrong, or you're baking your
own username and API key directly into
the string. So, it takes many forms.
We're also talking about certificates
themselves that contain a secret that if
I find a valid private key, then there's
a lot of things I can do with that. So,
these take many, many forms. But, it's
anything that can be represented as
plain text that when used grant access.
That's what we mean by secret.
And the secret sprawl?
Uh secret sprawl is the phenomenon
where, well, they get into plain text.
They get away from you. We put out this
report we'll talk about a bit later, the
state of secret sprawl report. And
that's specifically what we mean is
these have been leaked somewhere that is
accessible to someone aside from the
application itself, like in memory.
So, we talked right now about different
forms of secrets. You talked about
passwords, API keys, tokens,
certificates. Are there any other
flavors of secrets?
Oh, many. There's many ways to grant
this access as many systems as there are
on Earth. And there's a lot of systems
on Earth. But, it's just easier to
categorize them all together. It's
semantic differences at some point. And
there are systems out there that do make
a distinction between an authentication
key and an authorization mechanism, an
authorization token. That's actually
kind of an important distinction in my
opinion. We have married together this
world of authentication and
authorization in one form. We call that
the API key. If I have this key, then I
have standing privileges to do a thing.
That's not great because now it's a very
messy world. And when I revoke the
access, I'm also revoking the
authorization. But, also now I've tied
them together in a way that it's tricky
to say, "Look, you're allowed in, but
you're only allowed to do these things."
Because, again, that key is just the
key. Other problems is like they don't
expire by default. We're moving to a
world of certificates, X.509
certificates, and JWTs, JSON web tokens
that do have set expiration dates or
time periods when they're good for. But,
we're seeing that adoption lag cuz most
systems just traditionally used, "Hey,
this key gets you in and lets you do a
bunch of stuff.
Okay, so that brings me to my next
question which is where do you store
these secrets?
Ideally, you don't have to because
you've gotten rid of them and there's
many other ways you can approach access
and authorization that do not require a
long live secret or just in time access
that simply makes a token right when you
need one and that's the ideal situation
in our opinion. But the messy reality of
most companies is they have a ton of
these and the best next answer is
vaulting. They store them encrypted at
rest and only pull them into the
application when absolutely necessary
and for just long enough to actually be
used then immediately erased or dumped
from memory. There's plenty of providers
out there. I don't want to name all of
them but just so your audience know who
I'm talking about HashiCorp Vault.
There's OpenBao with a complete open
source project now based on that.
CyberArk has Conjur. Like I said,
there's many companies that provide
this. Delinia, Doppler. Vaulting
technologies aren't unique. There's a
lot of them but that leads to its own
problem of we have a lot of vaults and
now there's this phenomenon called vault
sprawl where wow, where do I put the
key? Which vault's the right vault? Are
we sure we rotated it correctly across
all the vaults? Like it leads to its own
world of problems. That's why I say it's
second best to a world where you're
accounting for identity and issuing just
in time access that's only available for
like one time only.
The last question I want to ask in the
definitions part of our podcast is who
produces this secret in the typical
software development life cycle?
That is going to depend on the company
and their particular governance.
Governance I don't think can be
productized. Governance is the end
result of a set of conversations,
decisions, what your hierarchy looks
like inside of your organization. But
the vast majority of these are simply
created by
developers who have the level of access
to make API keys, which is pretty much
every developer on Earth. If you think
of systems like GitHub, everyone with a
GitHub account can go and make a
personal access token. You think things
like Salesforce and HubSpot, you do need
a certain level of permission, but
developers tend to have that level of
permission because well, they're
developing. They need access to those
endpoints in order to get their job
done. So, the easiest way to think of it
is if I need access to an endpoint or to
make something happen on a platform, be
it a simple SaaS platform that does one
thing like Canva or a very broad
platform like AWS EC2 instances, you can
do anything on those things. That is
where these secrets come from.
Infrastructure and actual the world of
non-human identities that need to
connect together. It's a term that has a
lot of controversy around it because
you're defining a negative, but if you
think of workloads like in the
Kubernetes world or running pieces of
software that are executing within
larger contexts, that's where these keys
really are. That's where the secrets
really go to.
So, let's talk about how big the problem
is. And here I'm going to use the latest
Git Guardian report. And I'm quoting
from the report. The number of
hard-coded secrets such as API keys,
passwords, certificates pushed into Git
repos amount about 28.65 million in
2025, which is about a 34% increase
since 2024. So, can you talk a little
bit about these numbers and why it's
increased so much as per your analysis?
Absolutely. Well, so let me start by
explaining what we do and how we got to
these numbers. And that's by the way,
just public repositories, the numbers
you just listed. So, since 2018, we have
looked at every new commit that hits
GitHub in public. You can as well, it's
a public feed, api.github.com/events.
It's a firehose, almost 2 billion events
last year. We've never seen this much
code being pushed onto GitHub in public.
And we scan every new commit and every
new thing that becomes public that you
know used to be private. And we have
over 600 detectors on our platform. We
do contextual analysis as well, meaning
is this string being used in a way that
grants access or is it used in a way
that if it didn't grant access, then the
app wouldn't work. That's the easiest
way to think of it. That's a little more
detailed than that or nuanced. We send
an email to the committer right then and
there automatically. We call it our good
samaritan program. Your listeners
probably have gotten an email if they've
ever pushed code in their life. I know
that's how I discovered this company
existed years ago when I had shared my
private SSH key into a public repo by
accident. But yeah, just in the year
2025, that's not a cumulative number.
Just in the year 2025, we saw a 28.65
million hardcoded credentials or secrets
added to public GitHub repos.
That's a 34% increase over the previous
year. Again, not cumulatively. If you
look at the exact same methodology, went
back and applied the exact same
methodology to the commits that we had
seen back then, that's a 34% jump. Just
a lot.
And do you think cloud automations and
DevOps has made the secrets problem
worse?
Well, again, that's where the secrets
come from. More infrastructure, more
code, the more chances you're going to
hardcode a secret. The more confusing
you make the process or difficult you
make the process for the developer, the
more likely they are to say, "Well,
look, a hardcoded secret works. Uptime
is more important than any other
consideration. We're in a hurry here."
That is part of it. More code, more
problems. That's what I like to say.
The types of things we're building is
also shifted and I think we're going to
get into that a little bit later around
AI coding assistants and that. But if
you look at the actual infrastructure
that we're building, it is changing. It
is MCP servers now. It is things like
open router, which is a way to access
many of the LLMs. We're looking at
infrastructure that is not only just
new, but if you look at the config
templates, a lot of them just have the
hardcoded credential baked into it
because that's the easiest way to
communicate this is where the access
needs to occur. This is where it needs
to be accounted for. Unfortunately, a
lot of people that are coding now are
new to coding. This isn't just a new
person problem, by the way. I don't want
to blame like this is just new users.
It's people using different tools,
different platforms faster than we've
ever adopted anything else in history.
So, that is leading to all of this set
of mistakes. At the end of the day,
these are human mistakes that we could
have reviewed the code. We could have
used tools to prevent ourselves from
committing secrets, but we're moving too
fast for that, unfortunately.
Yeah, I think that's very interesting
that you bring up that we have a lot
more people touching a lot of these
surfaces than before. So, the pace is,
yeah, unprecedented. And if I looked at
the Verizon data breach in 2025 itself,
it said that the credential abuse and
phishing contributed to about 38% of the
attacks from last year. And one of the
things that a lot of people like on
Reddit forums and etc. talk about is
also these new risks of the AI coding
assistance, which you talked about,
which is almost fueling a lot more of
these leaks. A few days back, in fact, I
had a particular case where I was using
Claude with like this multiple
orchestration. And I was pretty much
surprised that I had this .env file,
which I had specifically told it was in
my gitignore. But when it was doing this
multiple orchestration, it still somehow
it figured that the .env file probably
had my credentials, and it spilled out
to me. And of course, then I went
through this whole process of rotating
my keys, etc. But based on this, what
really came to my like when you get
attacked personally is when you feel it
the most, right? Than actually talking
about it. It's what I then realized that
we have this new non-human identity
risks, which we hadn't really thought
about before. We also have this
non-human uses, which is going to be
using a lot of our secrets. So, I wanted
to find out from you if you could talk a
little bit about AI coding assistance,
but also talk a little bit about this
non-human identities which are using the
secrets and OS basically having now a
top 10 for this risk.
Sure. These are definitely highly
related things. At the end of the day,
all AI are non-human entities. They're
non-human identities. So, it's hard to
talk about them separately and in all
reality, I do think it's important to
draw a distinction between deterministic
and non-deterministic agentic versus
non-agentic when we talk about those
things. AI coding assistant that just
helps you complete a line of text within
your coding is different than an AI like
that you've experienced that spins up
another agent and somewhere along the
line says, you know what? This gitignore
file is in my way. We'll just ignore it.
Probably, that's what you wanted because
you wanted this end result and that's
the easiest way to get there based on
the vectors that I can glue together and
see what happens next. And there's like
some kind of hallucination happening
along the path to say, you know,
gitignore is is optional. What you're
describing there. But getting back to
the numbers, well, we've seen we
specifically looked at Claude code
co-signed commits. There's an ability to
annotate your git signatures with
additional signatures. And sometime in
very early 2025, Claude code added this
ability and we watched it get rapidly
adopted. At the same time, we watched
the number of secrets being committed by
those particular commits spike terribly.
By August, it was almost 4x the
baseline. Just to put it in perspective,
the baseline is 1.5 secrets per thousand
commit last year. I looked it up real
quick. It was 1.94 billion commits in
GitHub. That's 5.6% of all public repos
contain at least one hard-coded secret.
But when we look at Claude code across
the entire year, it was 2.4x the
baseline. But that was a massive spike
in August and then they released a newer
model. They updated the model and we
watched it ebb back down. Not go to
zero, not cross by the end of the year
it did not cross back underneath the
threshold for sure, but it started to
converge with the human baseline.
Unfortunately, the human baseline was
also ticking up. So, I think it's a
little inconclusive to say Claude code
makes you more likely to commit a
secret. What we think is happening with
Claude code is if you are allowing
Claude code to go ahead and make the
commit, that's what we think is
happening. And if you were cosigning
with Claude code, you're saying, "All
right, you made the code, Claude. Go
ahead and just commit it for me." Which
means you're probably not spending as
much time looking at what actually gone
on. Means you're probably not doing the
local testing. Means you're probably not
putting through the same rigor that you
would human produced code, putting the
right static checks in place to see
like, "Did I go to commit a secret?"
Pre-commit hooks. And again, as you
pointed out, there are times when Claude
could say, "Yeah, we're just going to
skip that. The git hook might get in my
way. Let's end around that." And it or
probabilistically that could happen. And
you gave it agency to go ahead and
affect the repo. That's kind of a
perfect storm of, "Yeah, eventually
you're going to do something where
you're just not going to run the test
and you're just going to push it and
it's going to yolo."
Well, I like the way you talked about
it. At the end of the day, you also have
to think of it as a tool and have the
very same set of checks that you had
with other tools that you used before.
The IEEE Computer Society is now
accepting candidates for the new
software professional certification.
Whether you're leveling up or ready to
lead teams, this certification validates
your expertise. Backed by the industry's
most trusted professional organization
in computing.
Visit computer.org/certification
to sign up today.
We talked a lot in this previous
question about secrets leaking through
code. What about logs, telemetry, and
even say debugging output, which I think
can be part of logs?
What do you think about that? That's
also a good vector, right, to get those
secrets?
A lot of people assume because Git is in
our name that that is our entire focus,
and it was back in 2018. But we're
[laughter] in 2026 now having this
conversation, and we have found secrets
basically in anything that can contain
text. Logs is a great example,
especially when we talk about the world
of a genetic AI. Any kind of AI LLM that
you talk to is basically a black box.
You know what you put in, and you know
what you got out. Now, I'm not saying
the entire system is like if you are
building a multi-agent system, there's
an ability to put some checks in between
those steps, but there's a place where
you can logically do it. But the actual
jokingly refer to it as a random number
generator, we don't know. We know what
we put in, we know what we got out. The
only way to tune it is to keep track of
what did we put in and what did we put
out. That's logs. That's one way to get
logs. I mean, we're talking above and
beyond like your Jenkins logs, your C I
C D runner logs, all the other logs.
We've been drowning in logs, and yes,
sometimes secrets do end up there, but
they also end up in places deliberately.
Jira tickets, Slack messages, someone
copy-pastes the thing into a
secrets.text file locally, screenshots
of like seed phrases. And you wouldn't
think that, okay, images, that's got to
be safe, right? No, we're actually
seeing recent attacks looking
specifically for any images with any
kind of Italian name, and then that's
OCR it. I think processing-wise, since
we're going to be running this stuff on
developer machines sooner than later
with throughout these attacks that we're
in like not care about the processing,
let's just look at all the images and
see if there's any valuable information
on there. It's a bit future-looking, but
we're already starting to see that
happen. So, secrets end up in so many
more places than code. It's very
important to start scanning basically
anything that has text within your
organization and realize that that, too,
is an exposure surface.
And while you're talking about this, I
also wanted to ask you about the
Kubernetes environments, right? The
secrets there when you mount a secret
point. I always find that a bit tough.
Like, it's clunky. You feel like that
could be a potential case for secrets
leakage. And if it's possible for you to
talk about some examples where you have
secrets leakages from Kubernetes, just
as an example, not quoting company
names, but just to give us an example of
what is a bad case of a Kubernetes
leaked secrets.
Yeah, without getting into specifics,
there are basically multiple ways to
approach Kubernetes secrets. The best is
to pull them in only when needed when
running, and then make sure they're
flushed from memory. That takes
architecture. That takes some retooling
of how you think about building your
pods, cuz the classic original way that
seemed safe enough at the time was let's
make a secrets folder and store them in
there. Or let's pull them in when the
pod is built, and then they're just
stored there. And they're just going to
live in that memory literally forever,
or until the pod dies, which is enough
time to exploit it. So, yeah, there's
many cases out there. I don't want to
pick on Kubernetes too much specifically
because I'm a big cloud native fan boy
out here, quite honestly. But yeah, it's
just one of the examples of how we can
build infrastructure insecurely by not
thinking about these access mechanisms
and who else might access them. I think
personally with Kubernetes, it's still a
bigger problem than even credential is
allowed to run as root. It's confusing
to get that security setting just right,
and if someone gets access to that box,
then my goodness, what can't they do if
they're running as root?
Yeah, game over. So, I think one of the
things I took away from your answer was
irrespective of the infrastructure,
whether it's Kubernetes or anything
else, I think it's a question of doing
just-in-time to prevent secrets leakage.
So, let's talk a little bit more when we
come on to mitigations about that. And
then the other thing I wanted to ask you
is also secret risks from leakage risks
from say third-party integrations and
SaaS tools. We've seen a lot of
examples. Can you talk a little bit
about that?
Yeah, the elephants in the room right
now, the big one from last year was the
Salesforce breach. I actually saw a
briefing on this from Cloudflare back at
RSA conference this year, where they're
pretty sure it started with one fairly
non-technical person finding one
Salesloft credential that was
over-privileged. Threw it against AI and
said, "What can I do with this?" and
then found a bunch of Salesforce
passwords, which ended up doing what
that did. I'm not going to get into the
full and details of that breach here,
but yes, third parties present this huge
challenge in a few different ways. The
biggest one is, well, if they can get
into that and you're storing your
information in there, then wow, they're
going to get your information. And
they're going to get access to your
keys. There's plenty of examples of
this, the Cloudflare Okta leading to the
Cloudflare breach a couple years ago.
Feels like yesterday, but just a couple
years ago, which is what I think we're
seeing now with Cisco like this week.
That's why Cisco's top of mind, where
it's literally a third party gets
compromised, but they had to have access
into your system. That ended Access into
the system was over-privileged, gave
whoever held that piece of data, that
connection string, a way to get in,
realize, "Hey, I can laterally move
around. I can live off the land in
here." and start stealing more
credentials and just keep the cycle
going.
So, I was just wondering, Dwyne, if you
could build up on that about the Cisco
leak for listeners who are not aware,
and I can also put access to one of the
news articles on the show notes. But can
you talk a little bit about this? So,
this is from the Aqua Security trivy
leak, right?
To be honest with you, this is an
ongoing attack right now, and anything I
would say, I would be repeating just
what's in the news out there. But, yeah,
Cisco's source code, and there's a group
called ShinyHunters, and their TTP,
their common tactics out there, are to
simply steal secrets somehow, and then
do bad stuff with it. And that's exactly
what we've seen. Cisco had over 3
million Salesforce records containing
personally identifiable information,
GitHub repositories, AWS S3 buckets, and
other internal corporate data have been
compromised and open-sourced, been
released onto the internet, where
basically anybody else can pick through
it, and wow, there's so much in there
that can be done. If you're listening to
this right now, and you are a Cisco
customer, I would highly recommend
rotating everything you have. And I wish
I was joking. I wish there was a simpler
explanation than that, simpler
remediation path than that. The people
that are going to do well out of that
are the people that can say, "All right,
run the automation script." And it just
rotates everything, cuz everything's
accounted for in a vault. Or, the people
that have already moved away from
secret-based authentication, and moved
to I shouldn't say away from, cuz
there's always going to be at the end of
the day, there's always going to be a
nonce. There's always going to be some
secret key somewhere. But, they've moved
to just-in-time, very short-lived things
that are based on the identities, not
the key existing.
Okay. And I think it would be good to
maybe go over a little bit about what we
saw last week, which is the supply chain
attack on the Aqua Security's GitHub
action, and Python's
that essentially used malicious
info-stealer malware to steal a bunch of
SSH keys, cloud credentials, Docker
configs, and even crypto wallets. So,
affected a range of companies. So, can
you talk a little bit about that for
listeners who don't know about this? And
I'm obviously going want refer to your
Snowball analysis report. I'll add that
to the show notes.
Thank you very much. So, I have a great
team. Shout out to Guillaume Valadon and
Gauthier Ferry who are on my team. They
are amazing researchers and they jumped
on this immediately and did a deep dive
and it culminates in the PC just
mentioned, but we have a couple others
like the one specifically about light at
LLM is where we released a tool. It's
free to use for any developer on Earth
to discover all of the secrets on your
machine and then put them in one
dashboard. Our dashboard, not the secret
itself, but like a reference to it and
then give you a risk score. You know,
like, "Hey, what order should I probably
deal with this in?" But, this is
unfortunately
not a novel attack. It's novel in the
fact that it's moving so fast and the
way that it's AI augmented and that it's
built on what worked well last year for
things like Shy Halud, uh the
singularity attack where the MO of the
attack is
let's just steal more credentials. Then
we can turn use those to automatically
infect things around it and
automatically steal more credentials. It
started, as far as we can tell, with
Aqua with about a month prior to So,
we're talking about them 6 weeks ago
now. There was a stolen credential from
a GitHub task runner. Believe it's task
runner, but a GitHub uh CI process.
A GitHub action, sorry. GitHub action
credential was stolen. I do believe in
my heart of hearts that Aqua thought
they had rotated everything. This is
very common out there. This is exactly
the story of Cloudflare when they
thought they had rotated everything and
they simply missed one and then the
attackers got in with an old credential.
That's exactly what happened. They were
able to compromise Trivy
based on the fact they could still
affect the CI/CD. Then it just started
spreading from there and it has
escalated, started Trivy went to the
rest of Aqua Sec kicks the Kubernetes I
forget I forget what kicks stands for.
But, from Checkmarx. It's a IAC tool,
infrastructure as code checking tool.
It's a great tool, except for that one
particular version that got compromised.
And that led to Those are well-used
tools, but I don't think they're
universal. I think they're loved by the
security community,
but are they on every developer machine?
No. Then we get to the world of light
LLM, which is
a step up in the attack, because that is
used by so many things. It's light LLM
is the open source framework for
connecting together all of these LLM
pieces. Like it call them well LLMs.
It's like your local version of of open
router. I'm oversimplifying, forgive me
for for oversimplifying a bit to your
audience. But that is massive. And then
that led to 2 days ago, Axios, not the
news site. It's interesting that there
is a news site about Axios, but Axios is
the HTTP library that runs basically
under everything. So, if you got a
package
and you implemented and you invoked the
Python environment whatsoever,
it just ran.
And now you have a credential stealer on
your machine. Everyone that's listening,
unfortunately, should feel like they are
compromised right now. That's a little
tin foil hat paranoia, but it's the
actual reality on the ground. Assume if
you have credentials for a production
environment, you should go ahead and
rotate those. Now, if it's for your
local stuff, it's your local like test
database, do whatever you want to do.
But if you have anything related to your
organization on your work machine right
now that could by itself let someone
into that environment, a secret, go
ahead and consider it compromised and
start rotating. And again, move away
from it if you can. I'm trying to figure
out the better way to have that
conversation with folks. I'd be honest
with you. Like we're good at helping you
understand and prioritize
the scope of this, but the actual what
do you do next is going to depend a lot
on how your organization has already
dealt with this. If you're already in
the process of rolling out things like
Ambit or Spiffy Spire for internal
stuff, then absolutely I would move
faster in that direction. If you have
vaulting systems that you can use, use
those. If you are completely without
anything, there are free open source
alternatives like KeePass. Download it.
There's even a great process open source
project called SOPS, SOPS. Forget what
it stands for, but it lets you encrypt
files at the line level in place. So,
it's a great way that, "Hey, I can't get
rid of this ENV file, but what I could
do is while it's on my machine not being
used, it's completely locked down and
garbage. So, anybody that found it, got
exfiltrated, it wouldn't do anybody any
good out there." So, don't mean to be
alarmist, but that's literally the
situation and how crazy it's gotten out
there right now.
Yeah, in fact we use it Axios even in
our front end. So, making for all the
HTTP get calls. So, I just upgraded
Axios, but I've not rotated the secrets,
so I'll do that after this. So, yeah,
thanks for that. I also wanted to ask
you about in light of these incidents,
right? What should organizations do when
they analyze these incidents? Are there
some common root causes? How can you go
about like fixing that? Like one of the
things you talked about before was
having these just-in-time secrets and
almost changing things architecturally.
But are there some I would say top three
items that teams should be looking at
when they want to do a root cause
analysis?
The first is these are well-known
indicators of compromise out there.
There's plenty of research being done.
There's some great resources I can point
you to. One that I started checking
every day of my life is
opensourcemalware.com.
It sounds like a scary place, but it's
it's really not. It's bot-driven thing
put together by some brilliant security
researchers, Paul Mccarty and Jen Giles,
and it's pretty real-time on keeping up
with supply chain attacks, keeping up
with malware that we're seeing out there
in the universe, and we're watching it
as we're watching it unfold in real
time. So, take a quick look. This is
where S-bombs come in really handy. In
fact, you could probably do some
automation to start getting mule alerts
if something on your S-bomb got popped.
And that is a good way to know. So, I
say be tin foil hatty and like if you're
not sure, just assume that you're
compromised. But, if you know, we don't
use any of this stuff. Like, nothing
that's been compromised is in my
environment. I would Okay. Feel a little
safer. But, still we need to move toward
getting a vault, get it encrypted as
quick as possible. And start with the
most critical for you. Now, that what
most critical means is going to depend
on
you and your governance. And like what's
critical for your business. So, if you
haven't ever mapped that out, like the
priority of if this gets popped, we're
all doomed, then that's a good bigger
step you should be taking from a posture
standpoint. But, yeah, ultimately, I
personally believe that we need to move
toward verifiable identity
as the thing that we permanently hold.
This works for humans fairly well cuz we
live in a world of passkeys. Not to say
that you know, you [laughter] know,
we're not your flawless at all. We make
a lot of mistakes. But, it's easy to
prove you are you at a certain level. Be
your thumbprint, be it your retina scan,
something that's uniquely you that's
verify you. Now, based on that, we can
start building trust from there,
transferable and transportable trust.
With machines, it's actually a little
bit easier at the end of the day. It
just takes a little bit of rethinking
what we're doing. So, instead of
standing privilege, you have standing
identity. And that identity doesn't do
anything other than prove you are you
from cryptographic proof. So, you are
running on this Unix socket. You're
communicating over this Unix socket. You
are on this stack. You are this user
agent. You were born at this time. We
have proof of all of this.
So, if I can carry that with me,
or the entity can carry it with it, then
there's all sorts of neat things you can
do. Spiffy, Spire is again cloud native
fan. So, that's where I would send
everybody to start. There's a great free
book everybody on the world should read.
It's called Solving the Bottom Turtle.
And the name comes from the fact that if
you put things in a vault, well, you
have to have a key to the vault. And
then, what do you do with that key?
Well, you put it in a better vault. And
then, you need a key for that. So, you
keep It's keys all the way down. It's
only when we move to hey, what's the
thing we know is absolutely true? Oh,
you're you. You can prove you're you.
Then, we can start thinking about
different ways to think about
authentication and authorization. So, I
could do things like uh AWS Security
Token Service is one of my favorite
things on Earth that exists cuz well,
now it's federated. I'll get to that in
a second, but you can take your
cryptographically provable identity to
this service, and it can do all the
checks and say, "Yes, here's a JWT or
JSON Web Token that lasts for 5 minutes
that will let you do
that'll let you prove you're you to
another entity. You take it to the other
entity, and it that whatever service
that it platform that sir whatever it is
does the verification step and say,
"Hey, is this real? Can we prove all of
this?" And it's only at that point
that we start talking about like what's
the intention here? And that's the other
piece. It has to be intent-based
thinking around identity. What is this
identity doing? Why is it here? What's
it supposed to be able to do? It doesn't
get standing privilege. So, we will
broker this out. It gets this role
if it crosses this threshold from AWS to
Azure
to specifically do this one thing on
this one service. And anyone that tries
to hijack that and tries to do anything
else is an automatic no. You're not
allowed in. Even if you could get your
hand on that token and work fast enough,
which I do believe we are starting to
see with just machine speeds and how
fast AI can do this stuff. Even if it
does that, it's like, "Okay, you get to
a wall." Like, "You're only supposed to
read out of this database. You can't
overwrite it. You're only supposed to
read these tables. You cannot read the
entire thing. You can only affect this
area
and limit that blast radius. At the end
of the day, attackers are going to
innovate and get around things. So, it's
all about limiting the blast radius as
as as possible. And the easiest way to
do that is simply get rid of standing
privilege. Get rid of long-lived
credentials and move to I think right
now anything else.
So use machine identities instead of
these whatever credentials long-lived
credentials. And for that is what you're
talking about SPIFFE and SPIRE. I just
looked it up online. SPIFFE stands for
secure production identity framework for
everyone and SPIRE is SPIFFE runtime
environment, right?
Yeah, SPIFFE runtime environment. It's
an open source implementation. And this
isn't the future. This project's 8 years
old and it's based off of stuff that
Google's been doing for over a decade.
You think Google handles API keys
between their servers? They haven't done
that in over a decade. SPIFFE came out
of basically open source people
realizing that and saying, "Wait a
minute. What if we just built this? What
if we just built this standard out?" And
we're actually seeing that get
interpreted into some really neat stuff
in the real world. Like I say, all the
platforms now, like all the big ones,
are supporting this idea of federated
identity where my token service can talk
to your token service
and then we'll figure out through
configuration and allow listing like
what you're allowed to do, what you're
not allowed to do.
Mhm.
This actually goes back to the problem
of SaaS and what we're seeing emerge
next. So right now the problem with SaaS
and third-party providers is well, I
need a way for us to authenticate
together and API key is the simplest way
to do that and that's why there's so
many and there's so much to clean up.
But there there's standards where SPIFFE
works internally very very well. It
works really well for Kubernetes. This
idea of federating that outside of your
platform, outside of your trust
boundary, that's fairly new. I've only
seen in that really emerge in the last
year where we talk about this platform
federation. And why STS from AWS
specifically is top of mind for me is it
was November Is it November's when I
learned about it, but I think they did
it in August. That's when they added
federation that hey, there's a way to
verify this even if you're on another
platform. There's a standard emerging
from the IETF um Internet Engineering
Task Force called Wimsey, Workload
Identity and Multi-System Environments.
And it's being drafted and it's the
conversation, but the rest of the world
is not waiting for the IETF to
officially grant and say this is the
officially the protocol. They're just
building it and thank goodness, but it's
recursive that the people that are
building this in the real world at some
very large organizations are also
saying, "Hey, this is how the standard
work for everyone." And it's like the
way HTTPS didn't used to be common. It
was you had HTTP site. HTTPS was like
"Why am I going this extra step? That
feels unnecessary." I remember living
through that. I'm old enough. Your
audience can't see me, but I remember I
grew a beard. I soon we will say, "Hey,
are you Wimsey compliant? Like, how do I
work with you across this standard?" And
we're already seeing it. It's just the
standardization of it is lagging a
little behind the reality of
future-looking enterprise. The early
adopters are already early adopting and
the latecomers and the people that are
reluctant, they're going to be dragged
into the future here very shortly. And I
personally believe the tax like we've
seen Trave, like the light LM, this is
only going to accelerate that. We need
to do something. We need to do something
now.
So, one of the ways that you're saying
engineering teams
should future-proof their secrets
management strategies, probably adopting
something like Wimsey.
I mean, Wimsey would just be the
standard underneath it. It's like saying
adopt TCP/IP. Like, no. It's just It's
just what we're going to build
everything against. Like, you're
compliant with the standard, therefore I
know how to talk to you. That's already
going to be set up. So, that's coming.
What engineering teams should be doing
right now is build a governance plan. I
know governance never sounds like the
right answer, but again, you don't buy
governance. There's no product that can
100% guarantee you grant you governance.
It's got like SOC 2 compliance. You
can't buy SOC 2 compliance. I mean,
people try to sell it, but man, you You
buy it. It's something you have to work
toward. You have to prove this is how
this works. And so, that's what
government plans really are is like what
state should these things be in? And
that starts really with understanding
what you have. If you're sitting there
and you're like, "I don't even know what
secrets
exist within my org?"
That's step one. Have some form of
common inventory. And that's across your
repos, that's across your vaults, that's
across your other SaaS platforms, that's
across your providers themselves. Like
if you don't know how many service
accounts you have in enter ID, that's a
good place to start. Let's just start
there. What do these things have access
to? If you think about it from like why
do you need a governance plan? Because
eventually auditors are going to knock
at your door if you're a sizable
organization. They're going to ask,
"What do you have? What state is it in?
Was it compromised? What remediation
steps have you taken to fix that?" And
if you have answers at the ready for all
of that, you're going to look pretty
good no matter what happens. Might still
be some bad days here and there because,
you know, it's tech, it's reality
happens. But you're going to be in a
much, much better position in the long
run if you just start there. Then you
can start building out like, "All right,
well, where should secrets live?" It's a
fun exercise actually if you maybe it's
not fun for everybody, but to sit there
and think, "All right, what are my most
mission-critical systems? How are we
storing secrets for that? How should we
be storing secrets for that? What's the
process of moving toward something
better than that?" And if you do that
system by system, it's a big process,
but just on paper, like you and your
team could do that in, you know, one
meeting and just say, "Okay, here's the
general plan. Are we all agreed to
this?" Now, that's how do we get to that
governance plan? And that's going to
depend on where you are with your
organization, how mature you are with
your tooling. And if you're a smaller
organization, it's like you don't think
you're going to be regulated for years,
you have the opportunity to say, "Look,
why are we doing the API thing? Why are
we making the same mistakes we made the
last 40 years in tech. We're building
brand new stuff with brand new
platforms. Let's figure out a better
brand new way, not even a brand new way,
but let's better out a better way to
handle this authentication and
authorization game.
That's great actually. That really got
me thinking. Even for small teams, if
you're building everything from scratch,
why not use something that's been
the latest and greatest like maybe
SPIFFE and SPIRE as you say, and build
it not with all the old problems.
Like my favorite personal story I had
from RSA was I was literally having a
conversation like this with someone who
was building a brand new platform. It's
a good idea for a SaaS idea. I'm
not going to share his name or like what
specifically, but he was talking to me
about this and it's like, "How do I need
your services?" And I'm like, "If you do
it right, you never will. You'll never
need get guardian because you're not
going to have any secrets to leak." And
he's like, "What do you mean?" And I
sent him the SPIFFE SPIRE book like
literally right then and there. I put
him up on LinkedIn. Two days later, he's
like, "This is exactly exactly what I
needed to know. Like we're doing this.
We're doing this not what I had planned
to do, which was all API keys and
vaults." I felt that was my biggest win.
Again, I see my entire job as help
people figure stuff out. I didn't say
that at the beginning of the show, but
that's really what drives me. And just
"Hey, here's what my product does and
here's how you use it" is very boring to
me. What's the bigger picture? What are
we moving to next and how do we get
there? That keeps me going every day.
Okay, so I guess if I have were to ask
you one practical piece of advice to
software engineers about
secrets and
reducing secret sprawl,
what would that be?
The number one thing is know what you
have. If you don't have
a full inventory, if you don't know for
sure what is on your machine, if you
don't know what for sure is in your
systems, there's no way to defend it.
That's rule number one of threat
modeling, know what you have. That's
never changed. That's never going to
change. The top 10 list that we didn't
really talk about when we didn't talk
about the OWASP top 10 for NHIs, which
is an awesome list. There's one for
LLMs, there's one for anything under the
sun. They're all great, but OWASP top 10
list are not prescriptive.
They are reflections of reality.
What are the actual problems we're
running into? Here it is. Can they be
solved? Maybe.
Will there always be a top 10 list? Yes,
that's how they work. Don't think of it
as like, if I do these 10 things, then
I'm safe. No, like those are the 10 most
common mistakes you can make. See it
that way and deal with those and you're
going to have a much, much better time.
If you look at the top 10 for NHI from
OWASP, I personally believe that it
breaks down into three buckets.
Ownership, like who sunsets this thing?
What does long-lived mean? The actual
long-lived secrets themselves, like the
technical like piece of data. Is it over
permissioned? What state is it in? Is it
leaked? And then the the technical
complexity of all this. The craziest
part of like everything I'm talking
about moving to these other
methodologies, these identity workload
identity based, they sound complicated
at first until you step back and realize
the reality of living with a world where
we have to account for a secret through
essentially obfuscation, through
encryption.
Like, if I get into your code and I see
that you're calling Vault
and I'm determined to get in, I'm going
to start looking for that Vault key cuz
there's a Vault key and I'm going to
start worrying to get in. If I get in
and see Spiffy IDs everywhere or calls
to Amazon STS, AWS STS, I'm going to get
discouraged cuz wow, there's no root key
I can just get into. Now I'm going to
actually have to own the platform in
order to do what I wanted to do. Much
harder, much more difficult path. Taking
over an entire CA versus just finding a
key.
That's the difference in technical
complexity. Maybe that doesn't matter to
an AI in the future, but for right now
it does. That's my great hope.
I think that's a great piece of advice
actually, stepping back and doing a
threat modeling exercise or maybe even
looking at your architecture, no matter
how big your team or your product is is
a great way of actually like finding out
what your true assets are and then
trying to see the good way to protect
them. So, I think that's a good piece of
advice. And I think that's something
that will stay with us. So, I will
definitely add that.
There's actually a free resource I'd
recommend everyone. You can even buy
paper copies of it, but OWASP has a
threat modeling exercise called
Cornucopia. They sell it as a game, it
is not a game. The video makes it
extremely clear this is a threat
modeling exercise you're going to do
with your entire team. Now, they do
gamify it a bit. I wouldn't say it's not
fun. It's it's actually enjoyable to
experience, but it's tabletop. It's
literally talking through if this
happens, what do we do? If these two
things happen, what's the higher
priority? It's having that level. Now,
that's across all AppSec, but it's a
really great resource to get your hands
on. I built a specific secrets version
of that, and if people reach out to me,
we can make those available. It's called
Spot the Secrets, and it's just this is
what hardcoded secrets look like inside
of little pieces of code or snippets.
Then we use a UV light to tell you if
you're right or not. I did that for Def
Con for AppSec Village a couple of years
ago. It doesn't really matter if you use
mine, use anybody's, just print
something out. Backdoors and Breaches is
another fun one. But tabletop, the more
conversations you have, the more you can
refine the plan. And conversation
shouldn't be in isolation. They should
always be in service of the larger
governance plan that you're trying to
put in place. If you don't have a
governance plan, if you're not talking
about governance plans, maybe it's time
to start.
That's really good. And I want to
actually ask you a couple more questions
in terms of, you know, detection. When
organizations discover that their secret
is leaked, one of the things you do is
of course rotate the secrets. What are
the other tools that one could use?
Like, how do you find out a secret is
leaked? Is that the place where I go to
opensourcemalware.com?
Opensourcemalware is about the ongoing
supply chain attacks and like what's
actually going on in these packages.
Guardian, a shameless here, we make a
tool that literally gives you that
insight. Secrets visibility is how I
always like to think about it. But, if
you're starting from scratch or starting
from nowhere, how I started actually
working at GitGuardian was I was talking
about building with open source
pre-commit hooks to like stop yourself
from committing known secrets. Like I
started with AWS secrets. It's still a
good project, but it's AWS specific.
There are open source or products out
there, better leaks from Akito now that
used to be GitLeaks. There are other
open source vendors out there. And if
you have nothing and you have no budget
whatsoever, you can use us for free if
you're an individual developer or try
one of these open source and just run it
locally. If you start with just your
local machine and you just start If you
just start with just what they were
looking for in the trivia attack or the
light element attack, what specifically
they were trying to dump and just start
there, it's pretty good start starting
point. But, there are many ways you can
do this. At the enterprise level, there
are a lot fewer options because you can
use grep to scan for patterns, but
unless you're doing the contextual
analysis of does this weird looking
string grant access? There are so many
ways around that. There are so many ways
to fool the trackers. And shockingly
enough, developers just want their code
to work. Doing it the right way
means it works.
Doing it the safe way
might not be the right way in their
opinion. It should be the same way. The
easiest path should be the safest path.
And that's what security teams If you're
a security person out there listening to
this, please work with your teams to
understand what they're doing, why
they're doing it. Help them adjust. Give
them better tools. Give them better
options than just paid. Don't hardcode
your secret and that's all the advice
you give them. That's good advice, but
wow, you need to give them a better
paths to not do that.
Struggling to advance in the software
industry?
As an experienced professional ready to
lead, pull ahead of your competition
with the new software professional
certification from IEEE Computer
Society.
Your expertise [music]
certified by the most trusted
professional organization in computing.
Take the lead in your career. Sign up at
computer.org/certification
today.
[music]
I was also thinking about these
sophisticated solutions like EDRs, which
is the endpoint detection. Would that
also help?
It depends. It honestly hasn't because
multiple reasons why that's the case
failing us. One, these are known
packages that don't have vulnerabilities
until they do. Like Trivy, well-trusted,
very good system. It wasn't until 47 of
the 48 tags or 48 of the 49 tags got
corrupted. And by the time we knew that,
the damage was done.
So, if you're looking for, hey, this CVE
is bad. We all agree. Don't run anything
with a CVE. But what happens when it
didn't have the CVE yesterday, and
that's when it updated, and by the time
we made the CVE, it was already million
people affected. That's why EDR
ultimately fails in this. The
unfortunate sad part here is if you have
credentials on your machine, and you are
using any kind of build system right
now, any kind of package manager, you're
susceptible
to this kind of attack. If you're using
Open VSX, the extensions for VS Code, or
all the things that use VS Code, that
ecosystem, that is also being actively
attacked right now where Make sure
you're trusting your sources. Make sure
you're pulling from very reputable
places. Pull them directly from vendors
if and when possible, but as we just saw
with Aqua, maybe that's not good enough
anymore. That's where players like
ChainGuard really stand out in my
opinion, where they do the work. They do
the work of rebuilding from scratch, and
you're pulling their version, not the
internet's version. They might pull the
corrupted thing into their sandbox, but
by the time you saw it, that malware is
gone. I mentioned them by name. There's
other people that do that out there, but
that's the reality we're facing now is
there's no good way to trust a binary
anymore. There's no good way to say we
trust you to never be compromised. And
that's why these recent attacks really
hit me as hard as they have. Like
personally, this freaks me out a bit.
I'm going to be complete open kimono.
Like complete open chest here. I'm a
little bothered by how fast this is all
happening and specifically what we're
seeing and what this means for the
developer life where I used to just have
environment variables on my local and
that was how it worked and that's just
that was safe. And you had to get a
remote access into my machine. You had
to look over my shoulder and hope that I
exposed one of those. And now it is
you trusted a security tool that was
keeping you safe up until it didn't. And
now everything in your machine is on the
internet is public.
I think that's a good place to end the
show on Dwayne. Thank you for coming on
SE Radio. I think you've given us a lot
of good tips. And before I let you go,
I'd have to ask you, where can people
find you on cyberspace?
I have a website that I actually vibe
coded. I'm very proud of it.
Dwayne-McDaniel.com
and that's got all my links.
GitGuardian.com
is my place of employment and I write a
lot on our blog. So if you go to
blog.gitguardian.com,
you will see my face or maybe not
immediately my face but you'll see my
name associated with a good number of
articles. I write a lot of recaps for
events. I go to a lot of events. So if
you're in North America, primarily I go
to North America. Maybe I'll see you at
a B-Sides or a DevOps Days or RSA or
Identiverse or Def Con. I get around.
Thank you once again.
Thank you.
This is Priyanka Raghavan for Software
Engineering Radio. Thanks for listening.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast including other episodes,
visit our website at SE-Radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter or
through our Slack channel at
SE-Radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.